{
    "OS":[
        {
        "index":1,
        "question":"1. Which process can be affected by other processes executing in the system?",
        "a":" cooperating process",
        "b":" child process",
        "c":" parent process",
        "d":" init process",
        "ans":"a"
        },

        {
        "index":2,
        "question":"2. When several processes access the same data concurrently and the outcome of the execution depends on the particular order in which the access takes place, is called?",
        "a":" dynamic condition",
        "b":" race condition",
        "c":" essential condition",
        "d":" critical condition",
        "ans":"b"
        },

        {
        "index":3,
        "question":"3. If a process is executing in its critical section, then no other processes can be executing in their critical section. This condition is called?",
        "a":" mutual exclusion",
        "b":" critical exclusion",
        "c":" synchronous exclusion",
        "d":" asynchronous exclusion",
        "ans":"a"
        },

        {
        "index":4,
        "question":"4. Which of the following is a synchronisation tool?",
        "a":" thread",
        "b":" pipe",
        "c":" semaphore",
        "d":" socket",
        "ans":"c"
            },


        {
        "index":5,
        "question":"5. A semaphore  is a shared integer variable_____",
        "a":" that can not drop below zero",
        "b":" that can not be more than zero",
        "c":" that can not drop below one",
        "d":" that can not be more than one",
        "ans":"a"
                },        

        {
        "index":6,
        "question":"6. Mutual exclusion can be provided by the ____________",
        "a":" mutex locks",
        "b":" binary semaphores",
        "c":" both mutex locks and binary semaphores",
        "d":" none of the mentioned",
        "ans":"c"
        }
    ],
    "CN":[
        {
        "index":1,
        "question":"1. When collection of various computers seems a single coherent system to its client, then it is called ________",
        "a":" Computer network",
        "b":" Distributed system",
        "c":" Networking System",
        "d":" Mail System",
        "ans":"b"
        },
        {
        "index":2,
        "question":"2. Two devices are in network if __________",
        "a":" a process in one device is able to exchange information with a process in another device",
        "b":" a process is running on both devices",
        "c":" PIDs of the processes running of different devices are same",
        "d":" a process is active and another is inactive",
        "ans":"a"
        },
        
        {
        "index":3,
        "question":"3. Which of the following computer networks is built on the top of another network?",
        "a":" prior network",
        "b":" chief network",
        "c":" prime network",
        "d":" overlay network",
        "ans":"d"
        },
            {
        "index":4,
        "question":"4. In computer network nodes are _________",
        "a":" the computer that originates the data",
        "b":" the computer that routes the data",
        "c":" the computer that terminates the data",
        "d":" all of the mentioned",
        "ans":"d"
        },
        {
        "index":5,
        "question":"5. Communication channel is shared by all the machines on the network in ________",
        "a":" broadcast network",
        "b":" unicast network",
        "c":" multicast network",
        "d":" anycast network",
        "ans":"a"
        },
        {
            "index":6,
            "question":"6. Bluetooth is an example of __________",
            "a":"  personal area network",
            "b":" local area network",
            "c":" virtual private network",
            "d":" wide area network",
            "ans":"a"
            }

    ]
   
}